{"tossups": [{"question": "In this nation, Garnet Wolseley captured the Sweet Water canal at the Battle of Tell El Kebir, ending the Urabi Revolt. The British occupation of this country began in 1882 and saw the rule of leaders like Fuad I. The ethnic Albanian Khedive Muhammad Ali ruled this nation with Sudan after he defeated the militant Mamluk Dynasty. Ferdinand de Lesseps built a large structure in this country, linking the Red Sea to the Mediterranean Sea. The Suez Canal was built in, for the point, what country that is led from Cairo?", "answer": "<b> Egypt</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This president authorized Marines to begin the U.S. occupation of Haiti. Edward House influenced the American position on a treaty negotiated by this president, which was opposed by the Irreconcilables in the Senate under Henry Cabot Lodge, Sr. This president called for the formation of the League of Nations as part of his Fourteen Points, which he incorporated into the Treaty of Versailles. For the point, name this US President during World War I.", "answer": "Woodrow<b> Wilson</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A metro stop in this city is named for James the Conqueror, who ruled from it. A park with a motif of ceramic lilies in this city was designed by the architect of a basilica with a cryptic magic square on its exterior that has been under construction for 90 years. This city is home to La Rambla as well as Park Guell and the Sagrada Familia. For the point, name this Spanish city that serves as the capital of Catalonia.", "answer": "<b> Barcelona</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "A 226 BC earthquake destroyed this island\u2019s bronze statue of Helios. For the point, name this Greek island famed for its Colossus.", "answer": "<b> Rhodes</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s \u201cCouncil Wars\u201d occurred when a faction of its Democratic Party split off to oppose Harold Washington, its first black mayor. A mayor of this city may have shouted an anti-Semitic slur at Senator Abraham Ribicoff after Ribicoff denounced his \u201cGestapo tactics\u201d at a convention held in this city. For the point, name this city where the 1968 Democratic National Convention took place during Richard J. Daley\u2019s mayorship and which has been led since 2011 by Rahm Emanuel.", "answer": "<b> Chicago</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Native American tribe that names this body of water were destroyed along with the Neutrals and the Tabacco peoples in a 1650s war against the Iroquois. American troops established a base in this body of water on Presque Isle. Put-in-Bay in this body of water was the site of a battle in which the captain of the<em> Lawrence</em>, Oliver Hazard Perry, defeated a British fleet. For the point, name this Great Lake that is connected to Lake Ontario via the Niagara River, the site of a crucial battle in the War of 1812.", "answer": "Lake<b> Erie</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A ruler of this dynasty asked the monk Drogon Chogyal Phagpa to create an alphabet to unify the written languages of the empire. Zhang Hongfan put down a resistance against this dynasty at the naval Battle of Yamen, but this dynasty ultimately fell to the Red Turban Rebellion. Strong storms called kamikazes prevented two invasions from this dynasty into Japan. For the point, name this Chinese dynasty that was established in 1271 by Kublai Khan.", "answer": "<b> Yuan</b> Dynasty (or<b> Mongol</b> Dynasty)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. Advocates for this action included Dr. Leona Baumgartner, who helped Elvis Presley take this action on<em> The Ed Sullivan Show</em> in October 1956; within six months, the national rate of this action went from 0.6% to 80% of the country. Over 1.8 million children took this action as part of the Francis Field Trial, then the world\u2019s largest medical experiment. The March of Dimes advocated for this action by funding the work of Albert Sabin and Jonas Salk, who invented two different methods of performing it. The production of iron lungs sharply fell thanks to, for the point, what type of medical care that prevents its recipients from contracting a paralytic disease?", "answer": "<b> polio vaccination</b> (accept descriptive answers related to getting a<b> vaccine</b> to prevent <b>polio</b>myelitis; accept any additional information; prompt on partial answers, like \u201cvaccination\u201d or \u201cpolio prevention\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Some prospectors in this industry were dubbed Wildcatters. Marion King Hubbert popularized the theory that U.S. production within this industry would \u201cpeak\u201d by the 1980s. J. Paul Getty and T. Boone Pickens were two industrialists who made their fortune in this industry, which boomed near the Bakken Formation in the Dakotas in the 21st century, partly due to the use of horizontal drilling. For the point, name this industry that produces petroleum.", "answer": "<b> oil</b> industry (accept<b> petroleum</b> industry before mentioned; do not accept natural gas)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Gordon Lightfoot\u2019s song \u201cBlack Day in July\u201d is about a riot in this city that caused Martha Reeves to cut short a performance at the Fox Theater. Journey\u2019s \u201cDon\u2019t Stop Believing\u201d claims there is a \u201csouth\u201dneighborhood of this city; in reality, Windsor, Ontario lies across this American city\u2019s namesake river. The Supremes, the Jackson 5, and Stevie Wonder worked for Motown Records in, for the point, what city whose 8 Mile Road inspired the name of a 2002 film starring Eminem, the largest city in Michigan?", "answer": "<b> Detroit</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "At the end of this event, Charles Borromeo wrote a namesake catechism. This event, which almost moved to Bologna, generated a list of banned books in 1564. According to legend, a mass by Giovanni da Palestrina convinced the participants in this event not to ban polyphonic music. This meeting, which was convened by Pope Paul III in a northern Italian town, declared the Vulgate to be the official Bible of the church canon. For the point, name this church council that fueled the Counter-Reformation and affirmed Catholic Church doctrine.", "answer": "Council of<b> Trent</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A work by this thinker says that \u201cTyranny, like hell, is not easily conquered; yet, [...] the harder the conflict, the more glorious the triumph;\u201d that work by this author opens by noting that \u201cthese are the times that try men\u2019s souls.\u201d This thinker wrote a treatise arguing it was impossible for an island to rule a continent; that work proposes an American alternative to the Magna Carta. For the point, name this revolutionary-era American thinker who wrote<em> The Age of Reason</em> and<em> Common Sense</em>.", "answer": "Thomas<b> Paine</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "In the aftermath of this event, Bernard de Launay was beaten and killed by a crowd at the Hotel de Ville. Prior to this event, soldiers named<em> invalides</em> [in-vah-LEED] had transferred gunpowder from the Hotel des Invalides to the site of this disturbance. The sacking of Jacques Necker as finance minister was one cause of this event, which occurred on July 14, 1789. For the point, name this event in which a Parisian prison was mobbed by a crowd, helping launch the French Revolution.", "answer": "<b> storming</b> of the<b> Bastille</b> (accepts synonyms for storming like<b> assault</b>,<b> attack</b>, etc.)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In the prelude to this war, forces under Seth Thornton were captured while on patrol. The losing side of this war later agreed to the Gadsden Purchase, allowing a rail connection between Los Angeles and Yuma. During this war, forces under Stephen Kearny captured Santa Fe without a fight. This war was ended with the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, which set part of an international boundary along the Rio Grande. For the point, name this war between the United States and its southern neighbor.", "answer": "<b> Mexican</b>-American War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "For the point, name this French-speaking province of Canada.", "answer": "<b> Quebec</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This novel\u2019s final chapter introduces a character known as the \u201cman who lay on his back,\u201d who is encountered in a dilapidated barn during a flood. This novel, whose only film adaptation was directed by John Ford the year after its publication, follows a family who find work as cotton and peach pickers after traveling along Route 66 to California The Joad family appears in, for the point, what Great Depression-era novel by John Steinbeck?", "answer": "The<b> Grapes of Wrath</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "Eugene Debs was arrested in this state for denouncing the \u201cJunkers of Wall Street\u201d in an antiwar speech. A group of unemployed workers were led by the businessman Jacob Coxey in a march on Washington from this state. Four students at a college in this state were killed during a protest against the invasion of Cambodia in 1970. The Kent State Massacre occurred in, for the point, what US state where environmental activism increased after the Cuyahoga [ky-uh-ho-ga] River caught fire in Cleveland?", "answer": "<b> Ohio</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This city adopted free-market policies under Sir John Cowperthwaite. A \u201cwalled city\u201d in this city remained ungoverned for centuries. This city is governed by the Basic Law under the \u201cone country, two systems\u201d doctrine. This city\u2019s New Territories lie across a narrow strait from its Lantau Island. This city was ceded to its former colonial overlords by the Treaty of Tianjin. For the point, name this city handed over by Britain to China in 1997.", "answer": "<b> Hong Kong</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In this city, the murder of Edmund Godfrey helped give credence to Titus Oates\u2019 invented claims. A king fled after attempting to arrest John Pym and four others in this city. Samuel Pepys\u2019 [PEEPS] diary records this city\u2019s last bubonic plague pandemic, as well as the devastating Great Fire of 1666. Sir Christopher Wren rebuilt St. Paul\u2019s Cathedral in, for the point, what capital city of the United Kingdom?", "answer": "<b> London</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This leader wrote<em> Glimpses of World History</em> from memory while imprisoned. This leader, who lost control of the Aksai Chin region during a war with China, claimed his country would \u201cawake to life and freedom\u201d \u201cat the stroke of the midnight hour\u201d in his \u201cTryst With Destiny\u201d speech. The law minister B. R. Ambedkar was appointed by this leader, the father of another of its prime ministers, Indira Gandhi. For the point, name this first Prime Minister of an independent India.", "answer": "Jawaharlal<b> Nehru</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}